[Music]
start with a right triangle with legs of
length a and b and hypotenuse of length
c
draw the circle containing the triangle
with radius of length c and given by the
hypotenuse
extend the leg labeled a to a full
diameter by adding the radius of length
c and a segment of length c minus a
connecting the lines from the ends of
this diameter to the top of the triangle
like this yields a right angled triangle
according to thaley's triangle theorem
consequently these two triangles sharing
an edge of length b are similar
this implies that c plus a over b
is equal to the quantity b over c minus
a
in turn
this implies that c plus a
times c minus a is equal to b squared
and expanding the product we get c
squared minus a squared is equal to b
squared so that c squared is equal to a
squared plus b squared this is the
pythagorean theorem
[Music]
you